<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Lainland</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Lainland</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 11:26:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sick Day</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/sick-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 11:26:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/sick-day/</guid>
      <description>&#xA;I&#39;m writing this post from bed today. I&#39;ve spent a lot of time in bed over the last week or two, which isn&#39;t unusual for me. This isn&#39;t a fun holiday or my lazy unemployed lifestyle; I have a chronic illness that keeps me in bed much of the time. &#xA;&#xA;Imagine the worst flu/covid infection you&#39;ve had and add a hangover on top. Your energy is sapped away and it&#39;s hard just to lift your head from the pillow. If someone told you they&#39;d give you £100 to walk down the street you&#39;d say &#34;fuck off&#34;. That&#39;s the kind of day I&#39;m having.&#xA;&#xA;I&#39;m unusually clear-minded today. Often my flare-ups come with brain fog that leave me watching Star Trek reruns in bed for days on end, but today my mind needs more stimulation than that. My body&#39;s no help though. A lot of my hobbies (spinning yarn, knitting, drawing, painting, whittling, ...) involve arm movement and a bit of core strength at the very least. Days like this can be the most dangerous because it&#39;s hard not to push myself past my limits just to pass the time. Even the muscle strength needed to hold my hands on the keyboard now is tiring. But if you&#39;ve ever been sick enough to watch tv in bed for days back-to-back, you know how quickly that gets old. &#xA;&#xA;That leaves me with reading and video games. I&#39;m off to do the latter (friend me on Steam @lainrr). </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Baby&#39;s first boucle</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/babys-first-boucle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 16:24:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/babys-first-boucle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I said in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://lainland.co.uk/posts/spinning/&#34;&gt;last spinning post&lt;/a&gt; that I had plans for both the undercoat and outercoat of the Shetland sheep&amp;rsquo;s fleece I had recently purchased. Today I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about the yarn I&amp;rsquo;m making with the soft downy undercoat.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My first foray into having a whole fleece delivered to our little flat started when my spouse told me about a knitting project they wanted to do. It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ravelry.com/patterns/library/kabine&#34;&gt;a very cute hooded vest&lt;/a&gt; made of a yarn that, when knitted up, makes a cozy teddy fabric.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The problem was, the yarn they needed to make this garnment was very, very expensive. The bulky boucle will run you £36 per 100g skein, and they needed 5 skeins. That&amp;rsquo;s £180 total, which is definitely over our yarn budget.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 800; --h: 800;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;skeins of boucle yarn&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/babys-first-boucle/Flette28atLoopLondon_800x800.webp&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;800&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Woolfolk Flette in Chalky Pink. Photo courtesy of Loop London&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The good new was, I had just heard of a book that would teach me exactly how to make any kind of boucle (and many other crazy yarns) I could possibly want.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, I told my love not to worry, and ordered a copy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.abebooks.co.uk/9781603427388/Spinners-Book-Yarn-Designs-Techniques-1603427384/plp&#34;&gt;The Spinner&amp;rsquo;s Book of Yarn Designs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; &gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;The Spinner&amp;rsquo;s Book of Yarn Designs&#34; src=&#34;&#34; &gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A boucle yarn is made of 3 different plys. A thin core, a thicker looping ply, and a thin binder. In the spinning world it is acceptable to use a storebought yarn as the core and sewing thread as the binder, but that would be too easy. I want really cohesive colour and bits of a different coloured core peeking out is not idea. Plus it feels silly to buy yarn for the core when I&amp;rsquo;ve got all this fleece lying around&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to waste any of the beautiful fibre I had worked so hard carding, so I practiced the looping on some stuff I had lying around. It takes two passes to ply this yarn. A first, holding the core yarn tight and letting the looping yarn coil around it loosely, then a second pass wrapping the binder around the first two plies to open the coils up into wavy little loops.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I found it quite tricky at first to get the right amount of the looping ply around the core. My handspun version will definitely not be as neat and consistant as the commercial yarn pictured above, but it should have a similar effect when knitted up.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; &gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Knitted swatches&#34; src=&#34;&#34; &gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Some knitted swatches of my practice boucle yarns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My spouse bought 300g of hand-painted roving for the looping ply and I&amp;rsquo;ve carded an additional 200g of the Shetland. I need 500g of yarn total, but as the looping ply is most of the bulk I&amp;rsquo;m being over-cautious and not counting the weight of the core or binder.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m shooting for 120 meters per 100g (this depends on how thick or thin I spin the yarn), so that means 600 meters of finished yarn. 3 plies means at least 1800m over all the plies, though it will realistically be more because the looping ply&amp;hellip; loops&amp;hellip; and needs to be longer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SO! That&amp;rsquo;s a lot of spinning! I&amp;rsquo;d better get started.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My new fibre hobby</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 14:42:32 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I started spinning (as in, hand-spinning yarn, with a spinning wheel) this summer. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been interested in textile in fibre arts and this seemed like an extreme but perhaps inevitable step. When I first saw spinners on social media I was surprised people still did that. I&amp;rsquo;ve since learned it&amp;rsquo;s not as fringe as I initially assumed and there&amp;rsquo;s a large community of spinners out there.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d already done sewing, knitting, crocheting, embroidery, cross stitch, and tatting. You could even go back to primary school and count bracelet making. I&amp;rsquo;d done most crafts you can do with a needle and thread and yarn. I could give &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobbin_lace&#34;&gt;bobbin lace&lt;/a&gt; a try, but I&amp;rsquo;m not much of a lace person and don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of interest in the final product.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What I am interested in is yarn. I use a lot of yarn, and as I&amp;rsquo;ve used more of it I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten a taste for the expensive stuff. Why spend £2 on a skein of acrylic yarn that will shed microplastics and make my hands sweat while I&amp;rsquo;m knitting when I could spend&amp;hellip; more&amp;hellip; but get lovely wool that&amp;rsquo;s soft and insulating and will last the rest of my life but is also biodegradable?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The thing is, sometimes I want a very specific colour and texture and my only options are very expensive. The yarn for my latest knitting project, a quilt-inspired cardigan, cost around £155. That&amp;rsquo;s more than I would pay for a cardigan from a shop, but this one is made in the colours I want, to my measurements, and if taken care of correctly could outlive me. And I had fun making it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The pattern is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ravelry.com/patterns/library/heirloom-quilt-cardigan&#34;&gt;Heirloom Quilt Cardigan&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ravelry.com/designers/katryn-seeburger&#34;&gt;Katryn Seeburger&lt;/a&gt;, if you&amp;rsquo;re interested.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 1290; --h: 1578;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Lain wearing a knitted cardigan with star-shaped quilt motifs. There are loose ends of yarn hanging from it.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/quilt-cardigan.png&#34; width=&#34;1290&#34; height=&#34;1578&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ignore the ends, I haven&amp;rsquo;t woven them in or blocked it yet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So how do I do more of that without spending all my money on hand-dyed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.springfarmalpacas.co.uk/alpaca-walking-2/unnamed-4/&#34;&gt;baby suri&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://loopknitting.com/collections/lace-weight-yarns/products/la-bien-aimee-kumo&#34;&gt;silk&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The answer appears to be buying a whole sheep fleece and spinning it myself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a bit daunting, to say the least. Spinners generally buy fleeces &amp;ldquo;raw&amp;rdquo;, which means it&amp;rsquo;s still as dirty as it was on the sheep (though it&amp;rsquo;s hopefully been skirted (had any poo/stained bits removed)). The fleece will need washing to remove the dirt and pieces of hay and lanolin (the natural oil produced by the sheep which is solid at room temperature).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(At this point I feel it necessary to point out the difference between a fleece and a pelt. Spinners are not using sheep pelts with the skin on them. When I&amp;rsquo;m talking about sheep fleeces, I mean the wool that is removed from the sheep when it gets a haircut once or twice a year. This does not involve killing the sheep or even hurting it. On the contrary, sheep need to be shorn to stay healthy. Okay, back to the fibre talk.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was able to find &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.benridgewoolworks.co.uk/&#34;&gt;a company&lt;/a&gt; that sells british fleeces and has a wash and dry service. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have the energy to hand wash and rinse (at least twice) 1-3kg of wool and I definitely don&amp;rsquo;t have the space to dry it. (Glasgow has an &lt;a href=&#34;https://weather-and-climate.com/average-monthly-Humidity-perc,glasgow-gb,United-Kingdom&#34;&gt;average humidity of 79%&lt;/a&gt; over the year. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to dry laundry even with our dehumidifier on every day all year round.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, I ordered my first fleece! I decided on a beige &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shetland_sheep&#34;&gt;Shetland&lt;/a&gt;(the website said beige but I think it looks like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shetland_sheep#Colours_and_patterns&#34;&gt;musket or moorit&lt;/a&gt; - either way, it&amp;rsquo;s not beige), which was maybe a bold choice for my first. Shetland sheep are a &amp;lsquo;primitive&amp;rsquo; breed, which basically means old/ not cross-bred in recent history. They have a double coat, with an outer hairy layer and a soft, downy undercoat. Both are usable, but I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to pull them apart and process them separately.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 1234; --h: 1640;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/fleece-closeup.png&#34; width=&#34;1234&#34; height=&#34;1640&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;A close-up of the fleece as it arrived, showing the crimpy, soft, undercoat on the left and some locks of the long, hairy outercoat on the right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where I&amp;rsquo;m at so far:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;30g undercoat, carded and ready to spin&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;29g (undercoat) and 40g (outercoat), separated, not yet carded&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;736g unseparated but mostly clean&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 1234; --h: 1648;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;A fleece in various stages of processing&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/fleece-processing.png&#34; width=&#34;1234&#34; height=&#34;1648&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Bottom: around 1/3 of the total fleece, unseparated and as it arrived&#xA;Top right: separated wool, with the outercoat above and the undercoat below&#xA;Top left: carded undercoat ready to spin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a really beautiful fleece with a lot of colour variation and the undercoat is so so soft.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have plans for both the undercoat and the outercoat - more on that next time!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Edit: In an earlier version of this post, I forgot to talk about the price of fleeces. Obviously they&amp;rsquo;re a lot cheaper than their weight in yarn. While the different yarns for my cardigan cost between £10 and £30 per 100g, the whole fleece plus the wash and dry service cost £25.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My favourite citizen scientist projects</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Oct 2025 08:24:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I spend &lt;del&gt;a lot&lt;/del&gt; a reasonable amount of time on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/&#34;&gt;Zooniverse.org&lt;/a&gt;, a site that allows regular people to contribute to scientific research in a range of fields. Generally, most projects will have you look at an image or video and enter a couple of data points about it, generally identifying things that a computer may have missed in a large dataset. It&amp;rsquo;s a fun way to spend a few minutes that may have otherwise been spent doomscrolling.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I started on a project called &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/mschwamb/planet-hunters-ngts&#34;&gt;Planet Hunters NGTS&lt;/a&gt; which uses data from the Next-Generation Transit Survey to look for exoplanets (planets outside our solar system). I&amp;rsquo;m &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; interested in exoplanets (currently-doing-an-integrated-master&amp;rsquo;s-degree-in-astrophysics level of interest) and I wanted to know what transit data looked like. What better way than sorting through a bunch of it looking for exoplanets?! Very exciting.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Obviously I&amp;rsquo;m keen on the space-themed projects, but there are a lot of other areas of research that I&amp;rsquo;ve had fun contributing towards. I&amp;rsquo;ve identified fish species in Aotearoa, transcribed 1960&amp;rsquo;s weather data from modern day Burkina Faso (that project is paused for now so it&amp;rsquo;s not listed below), and labeled tags on spoonbills in France.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Below are some projects I found interesting that you may want to take a look at.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;planet-hunters-ngts-and-planet-hunters-tess&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/mschwamb/planet-hunters-ngts&#34;&gt;Planet Hunters NGTS&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/nora-dot-eisner/planet-hunters-tess&#34;&gt;Planet Hunters TESS&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#planet-hunters-ngts-and-planet-hunters-tess&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;There are TWO projects on Zooniverse looking for exoplanets! My lucky day!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Both of these projects are looking for transiting exoplanets. We can&amp;rsquo;t literally &lt;em&gt;see&lt;/em&gt; exoplanets (with a couple of crazy exceptions), because they&amp;rsquo;re too dim and tiny and they&amp;rsquo;re right next to a literal star, but thankfully there are other ways we can detect them.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Basically, an exoplanet transits if its orbit around its star aligns so it passes in front of the star from our perspective. When this happens, we can see the light from the star get a bit dimmer (because the planet is blocking a small percentage of the light). If we see the same dimming happen on a regular schedule, then we know a planet is transiting the star!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/51_Pegasi_b&#34;&gt;The first exoplanet&lt;/a&gt; was discovered in 1995 and as of writing we&amp;rsquo;ve found &lt;a href=&#34;https://exoplanet.eu/home/&#34;&gt;7762 exoplanets&lt;/a&gt;! Let&amp;rsquo;s find some more!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 2300; --h: 1292;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Discover hidden worlds with the Next Generation Transit Survey&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/NGTS.png&#34; width=&#34;2300&#34; height=&#34;1292&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;sudan-road-access&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/alicemead/sudan-road-access-logistics-cluster&#34;&gt;Sudan Road Access&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#sudan-road-access&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In this project, you use satellite images to identify wadis (dry river beds) in Sudan. This helps humanitarian aid drivers avoid the rivers when they flood and block roads.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 2460; --h: 1006;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;A screenshot showing satellite images of Sudan, with roads and wadis visible.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/SudanRoadAccess.png&#34; width=&#34;2460&#34; height=&#34;1006&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;From the project description:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This project maps key road supply routes for humanitarian aid to reach Sudan. The impending rainy season will likely cut off critical supply routes, as wadis (dry riverbeds) can fill up and flood roads.&#xA;We need to map where wadis cross over roads to help aid organisations plan delivery routes. The data we generate will be crucial for informing humanitarians so aid can reach the people who need it most in the largest displacement crisis in the world, where millions of people are facing starvation.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This project is 93% complete as of writing, but I believe they add more images to classify periodically, so I&amp;rsquo;m sure there&amp;rsquo;s more to do. I haven&amp;rsquo;t encountered any, but this project does warn that there&amp;rsquo;s a risk of disturbing images, so maybe try a different project if you&amp;rsquo;re not in a good headspace.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;spyfish-aotearoa&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/victorav/spyfish-aotearoa&#34;&gt;Spyfish Aotearoa&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#spyfish-aotearoa&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 2440; --h: 1402;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Kia ora and welcome to Aotearoa New Zealand&amp;rsquo;s underwater world! Discover, count and identify unique fish species from marine reserves.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/SpyfishAotearoa.png&#34; width=&#34;2440&#34; height=&#34;1402&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This one is a challenge and really gratifying when you start to get it! Watch 10 second underwater clips of fish, then identify how many of what species are there. Theres a field guide to help you identify fish species and it gets easier as you go along.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 2436; --h: 1532;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;A screenshot of the project&amp;rsquo;s interface. A video with a fish is paused and there is a red square around the fish. There is another image of a fish labeled &amp;lsquo;Blue cod&amp;rsquo;. There is an arrow to the fish in the video and text: I found him!&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/SpyfishAotearoa2.png&#34; width=&#34;2436&#34; height=&#34;1532&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;black-hole-hunters&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/cobalt-lensing/black-hole-hunters&#34;&gt;Black Hole Hunters&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#black-hole-hunters&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 2452; --h: 1652;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Illustration of a black hole. Text: Making the invisible visible.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/BlackHoleHunters.png&#34; width=&#34;2452&#34; height=&#34;1652&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Black holes are fucking sick.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;beluga-bits&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/stephenresearch/beluga-bits&#34;&gt;Beluga Bits&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#beluga-bits&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;During the summer thousands of beluga whales visit the estuary and at that time &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.Explore.org&#34;&gt;www.Explore.org&lt;/a&gt; runs a live-streaming underwater video from a zodiac that people around the world can view. During the beluga season (from mid-July until the end of August) we ask viewers to capture snapshots when they see beluga or other interesting species in the estuary.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I really like belugas. Probably because of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=mIBY-LQYkVA&#34;&gt;the Raffi song&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 2442; --h: 1208;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Image of beluga whales swimming underwater. Text: Examine underwater photos of wild beluga whales and help us identify the age, sex, and group size. We also need keen eyes to look for identifying marks to recognize beluga that return to this location year after year.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/BelugaBits.png&#34; width=&#34;2442&#34; height=&#34;1208&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h1 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;where-is-spoony&#34;&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.zooniverse.org/projects/hugo-ferreira/where-is-spoony&#34;&gt;Where is Spoony?&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#where-is-spoony&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h1&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Researchers in Camargue, Southern France plant cameras in the Eurasian Spoonbill&amp;rsquo;s breeding area and tag the birds with individual codes. You get to review stills and try to identify the codes. It&amp;rsquo;s a bit like Where&amp;rsquo;s Waldo/Wally spotting the little tags on the birds&amp;rsquo; legs. I find it rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 1768; --h: 342;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Three stills from video showing spoonbills standing and sitting on the ground.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/Spoonbills.png&#34; width=&#34;1768&#34; height=&#34;342&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Plus, the birds are hilarious.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 432; --h: 412;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Funny photo of a spoonbill biting the camera.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/my-favourite-citizen-scientist-projects/Spoony.png&#34; width=&#34;432&#34; height=&#34;412&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In all of these projects, you will need to do a bit of guesswork. It can be tempting to say &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if this is right, I&amp;rsquo;ll just skip this one&amp;rdquo;, but it&amp;rsquo;s worth noting that every photo/video/piece of data is classified by multiple volunteers, so if you&amp;rsquo;re wrong someone will catch it. It&amp;rsquo;s much more helpful to give your best guess.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s really quick to get started with any of these projects, so give it a go and contribute to science!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why I&#39;m starting a personal blog in 2025</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/post-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 08:24:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/post-1/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, my first post on my new blog, anytime near my writing it, you probably know me in real life and are here because I sent you the link. So you probably know that I&amp;rsquo;ve not been very active (or at all active) on social media since the good old days of an ad-free, chronologically-organised Instagram.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I deleted facebook in 2014. (Though briefly reinstated it in 2015 when I lost my phone in the Faroe Islands and it was my only way of contacting anyone back home.) (Maybe more about that another time.) I&amp;rsquo;ve had Instagram since 2011 or so but have never really kept up with it. Lately, I open the app, get barraged by ads and posts from people I don&amp;rsquo;t follow, and close it within 30 seconds. I also just don&amp;rsquo;t take enough highly-polished pictures of myself/my home/life to post. Everyone else seems to be doing these monthly round-ups of highly-polished aesthetic photos and I just have 20 pictures of my cat with junk in the background.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And sure, I could post those pictures of my adorable cat and say fuck being polished. Maybe my doing that would be the tiniest nudge toward making Instagram a more enjoyable and realistic place. But, there&amp;rsquo;s still the ads, and the data mining, and the fact that Meta owns all the images on Instagram&amp;hellip; and here I go closing the app again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So instead, my social media use has become lurking on TikTok and tumblr, never posting any of my own stuff. But this is a very different experience than the friendly back-and-forth sharing I used to have with friends and family back in the day. It&amp;rsquo;s more like watching tv, except with more ads and each show is 2 minutes long and full of misinformation (and I skip most of them after 3 seconds).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So how do I keep in touch with my friends and family, nearly all of whom live far away, often with a time difference? I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to go with a combination of trying to keep on top of my messages better and trying to herd everyone I know onto the small web.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re not familiar with the term &amp;lsquo;small web&amp;rsquo;, it&amp;rsquo;s basically a return to the early days of the internet when people had personal websites and everything wasn&amp;rsquo;t owned by 4 enormous companies. There&amp;rsquo;s a good (somewhat technical) explainer about it &lt;a href=&#34;https://benhoyt.com/writings/the-small-web-is-beautiful/&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, instead of trying to force myself to use Instagram &lt;em&gt;again&lt;/em&gt;, I set up an RSS reader.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h2 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;what-is-an-rss-reader-and-why-should-i-have-one&#34;&gt;&#xA;  What is an RSS reader and why should I have one?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#what-is-an-rss-reader-and-why-should-i-have-one&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h2&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;An RSS reader is a bit like an email inbox, but for websites you subscribe to. Or, you can think of it as a podcast feed but for reading. Basically, it works by maintaining a list of website feeds you want updates from, checking to see if there have been updates, and organising them for you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 3022; --h: 1780;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;A screenshot of Lain&amp;rsquo;s RSS reader open to a blog post about rogue planets.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/post-1/RSS-screenshot.png&#34; width=&#34;3022&#34; height=&#34;1780&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;A screenshot of my RSS reader, NetNewsWire.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can add a link to pretty much any website that has a feed, but it&amp;rsquo;s best for blogs and news feeds that don&amp;rsquo;t update very often. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to check if there&amp;rsquo;s a new post on the website because it shows up automatically in your RSS reader.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is an ideal way to keep up with blogs like the one you&amp;rsquo;re reading now. I have categories for different topics, including:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Space&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;My local astronomical society&amp;rsquo;s news feed&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Some independent astronomy blogs&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Updates from NASA&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://science.nasa.gov/mission/europa-clipper/&#34;&gt;Europa Clipper&lt;/a&gt; mission (which is what got me into astronomy and astrophysics)&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comics&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Just the wonderful &lt;a href=&#34;https://xkcd.com/&#34;&gt;xkcd&lt;/a&gt; so far&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Games&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;Now I won&amp;rsquo;t miss updates on Concerned Ape (the creator of Stardew Valley)&amp;rsquo;s new game &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.hauntedchocolatier.net/&#34;&gt;Haunted Chocolatier&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You may now be thinking, &amp;ldquo;Okay, but I don&amp;rsquo;t read any blogs. I&amp;rsquo;m not sure how to find any that would be interesting to me.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;rsquo;s understandable! We&amp;rsquo;re not used to looking for interesting things on the internet anymore. Now, you just open an app and watch/read whatever is served up to you.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The good news is, the only way for people to find these blogs are for people to make collections of them. A lot of blogs also have a list of other blogs they recommend. &lt;a href=&#34;https://blogroll.org/&#34;&gt;Blogroll&lt;/a&gt; is a great place to get started, but you can also just google (or DuckDuckGo, if we&amp;rsquo;re avoiding the big tech companies) &amp;lsquo;[interest] blog&amp;rsquo;. That&amp;rsquo;s how I found some of my favourite astronomy blogs.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;You can set up an RSS reader for your browser or download a native app like I did. There are paid platforms but also some good free ones. &lt;a href=&#34;https://netnewswire.com/&#34;&gt;NetNewsWire&lt;/a&gt; is a great free and open-source RSS reader for Apple devices.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;hr&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;While I can&amp;rsquo;t imagine all my friends and family setting up blogs immediately (or ever), it would be incredible to have a folder full of personal blogs of people I know in real life sending me all their random thoughts and weird interests. Why should all my communication with my friends in other cities and my family across an ocean be owned by Meta? I&amp;rsquo;m no longer letting &amp;ldquo;the algorithm&amp;rdquo; decide what I see/read/know about.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;One last thing about the small internet:&#xA;Since I set up my RSS reader and started intentionally looking for small websites and personal blogs, I&amp;rsquo;ve not seen one with a pop up asking me to enable cookies. I&amp;rsquo;ve not even gotten a pop up asking me to sign up to their newsletter. They don&amp;rsquo;t want my email address, because they use RSS feeds! I&amp;rsquo;m starting to like the internet again.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>