<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chronic Illness on Lainland</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/tags/chronic-illness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chronic Illness on Lainland</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 11:26:34 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/lainland/tags/chronic-illness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sick Day</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/sick-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jan 2026 11:26:34 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/sick-day/</guid>
      <description>&#xA;I&#39;m writing this post from bed today. I&#39;ve spent a lot of time in bed over the last week or two, which isn&#39;t unusual for me. This isn&#39;t a fun holiday or my lazy unemployed lifestyle; I have a chronic illness that keeps me in bed much of the time. &#xA;&#xA;Imagine the worst flu/covid infection you&#39;ve had and add a hangover on top. Your energy is sapped away and it&#39;s hard just to lift your head from the pillow. If someone told you they&#39;d give you £100 to walk down the street you&#39;d say &#34;fuck off&#34;. That&#39;s the kind of day I&#39;m having.&#xA;&#xA;I&#39;m unusually clear-minded today. Often my flare-ups come with brain fog that leave me watching Star Trek reruns in bed for days on end, but today my mind needs more stimulation than that. My body&#39;s no help though. A lot of my hobbies (spinning yarn, knitting, drawing, painting, whittling, ...) involve arm movement and a bit of core strength at the very least. Days like this can be the most dangerous because it&#39;s hard not to push myself past my limits just to pass the time. Even the muscle strength needed to hold my hands on the keyboard now is tiring. But if you&#39;ve ever been sick enough to watch tv in bed for days back-to-back, you know how quickly that gets old. &#xA;&#xA;That leaves me with reading and video games. I&#39;m off to do the latter (friend me on Steam @lainrr). </description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>