<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Spinning on Lainland</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/tags/spinning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Spinning on Lainland</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 16:24:44 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/lainland/tags/spinning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Baby&#39;s first boucle</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/babys-first-boucle/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Nov 2025 16:24:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/babys-first-boucle/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I said in my &lt;a href=&#34;http://lainland.co.uk/posts/spinning/&#34;&gt;last spinning post&lt;/a&gt; that I had plans for both the undercoat and outercoat of the Shetland sheep&amp;rsquo;s fleece I had recently purchased. Today I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about the yarn I&amp;rsquo;m making with the soft downy undercoat.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My first foray into having a whole fleece delivered to our little flat started when my spouse told me about a knitting project they wanted to do. It&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ravelry.com/patterns/library/kabine&#34;&gt;a very cute hooded vest&lt;/a&gt; made of a yarn that, when knitted up, makes a cozy teddy fabric.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The problem was, the yarn they needed to make this garnment was very, very expensive. The bulky boucle will run you £36 per 100g skein, and they needed 5 skeins. That&amp;rsquo;s £180 total, which is definitely over our yarn budget.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 800; --h: 800;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;skeins of boucle yarn&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/babys-first-boucle/Flette28atLoopLondon_800x800.webp&#34; width=&#34;800&#34; height=&#34;800&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Woolfolk Flette in Chalky Pink. Photo courtesy of Loop London&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The good new was, I had just heard of a book that would teach me exactly how to make any kind of boucle (and many other crazy yarns) I could possibly want.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, I told my love not to worry, and ordered a copy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.abebooks.co.uk/9781603427388/Spinners-Book-Yarn-Designs-Techniques-1603427384/plp&#34;&gt;The Spinner&amp;rsquo;s Book of Yarn Designs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; &gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;The Spinner&amp;rsquo;s Book of Yarn Designs&#34; src=&#34;&#34; &gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;A boucle yarn is made of 3 different plys. A thin core, a thicker looping ply, and a thin binder. In the spinning world it is acceptable to use a storebought yarn as the core and sewing thread as the binder, but that would be too easy. I want really cohesive colour and bits of a different coloured core peeking out is not idea. Plus it feels silly to buy yarn for the core when I&amp;rsquo;ve got all this fleece lying around&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to waste any of the beautiful fibre I had worked so hard carding, so I practiced the looping on some stuff I had lying around. It takes two passes to ply this yarn. A first, holding the core yarn tight and letting the looping yarn coil around it loosely, then a second pass wrapping the binder around the first two plies to open the coils up into wavy little loops.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I found it quite tricky at first to get the right amount of the looping ply around the core. My handspun version will definitely not be as neat and consistant as the commercial yarn pictured above, but it should have a similar effect when knitted up.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; &gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Knitted swatches&#34; src=&#34;&#34; &gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Some knitted swatches of my practice boucle yarns&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;My spouse bought 300g of hand-painted roving for the looping ply and I&amp;rsquo;ve carded an additional 200g of the Shetland. I need 500g of yarn total, but as the looping ply is most of the bulk I&amp;rsquo;m being over-cautious and not counting the weight of the core or binder.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m shooting for 120 meters per 100g (this depends on how thick or thin I spin the yarn), so that means 600 meters of finished yarn. 3 plies means at least 1800m over all the plies, though it will realistically be more because the looping ply&amp;hellip; loops&amp;hellip; and needs to be longer.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;SO! That&amp;rsquo;s a lot of spinning! I&amp;rsquo;d better get started.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My new fibre hobby</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 14:42:32 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I started spinning (as in, hand-spinning yarn, with a spinning wheel) this summer. I&amp;rsquo;ve always been interested in textile in fibre arts and this seemed like an extreme but perhaps inevitable step. When I first saw spinners on social media I was surprised people still did that. I&amp;rsquo;ve since learned it&amp;rsquo;s not as fringe as I initially assumed and there&amp;rsquo;s a large community of spinners out there.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d already done sewing, knitting, crocheting, embroidery, cross stitch, and tatting. You could even go back to primary school and count bracelet making. I&amp;rsquo;d done most crafts you can do with a needle and thread and yarn. I could give &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bobbin_lace&#34;&gt;bobbin lace&lt;/a&gt; a try, but I&amp;rsquo;m not much of a lace person and don&amp;rsquo;t have a lot of interest in the final product.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;What I am interested in is yarn. I use a lot of yarn, and as I&amp;rsquo;ve used more of it I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten a taste for the expensive stuff. Why spend £2 on a skein of acrylic yarn that will shed microplastics and make my hands sweat while I&amp;rsquo;m knitting when I could spend&amp;hellip; more&amp;hellip; but get lovely wool that&amp;rsquo;s soft and insulating and will last the rest of my life but is also biodegradable?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The thing is, sometimes I want a very specific colour and texture and my only options are very expensive. The yarn for my latest knitting project, a quilt-inspired cardigan, cost around £155. That&amp;rsquo;s more than I would pay for a cardigan from a shop, but this one is made in the colours I want, to my measurements, and if taken care of correctly could outlive me. And I had fun making it.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(The pattern is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ravelry.com/patterns/library/heirloom-quilt-cardigan&#34;&gt;Heirloom Quilt Cardigan&lt;/a&gt; by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ravelry.com/designers/katryn-seeburger&#34;&gt;Katryn Seeburger&lt;/a&gt;, if you&amp;rsquo;re interested.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 1290; --h: 1578;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;Lain wearing a knitted cardigan with star-shaped quilt motifs. There are loose ends of yarn hanging from it.&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/quilt-cardigan.png&#34; width=&#34;1290&#34; height=&#34;1578&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ignore the ends, I haven&amp;rsquo;t woven them in or blocked it yet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So how do I do more of that without spending all my money on hand-dyed &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.springfarmalpacas.co.uk/alpaca-walking-2/unnamed-4/&#34;&gt;baby suri&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://loopknitting.com/collections/lace-weight-yarns/products/la-bien-aimee-kumo&#34;&gt;silk&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;The answer appears to be buying a whole sheep fleece and spinning it myself.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;This is a bit daunting, to say the least. Spinners generally buy fleeces &amp;ldquo;raw&amp;rdquo;, which means it&amp;rsquo;s still as dirty as it was on the sheep (though it&amp;rsquo;s hopefully been skirted (had any poo/stained bits removed)). The fleece will need washing to remove the dirt and pieces of hay and lanolin (the natural oil produced by the sheep which is solid at room temperature).&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;(At this point I feel it necessary to point out the difference between a fleece and a pelt. Spinners are not using sheep pelts with the skin on them. When I&amp;rsquo;m talking about sheep fleeces, I mean the wool that is removed from the sheep when it gets a haircut once or twice a year. This does not involve killing the sheep or even hurting it. On the contrary, sheep need to be shorn to stay healthy. Okay, back to the fibre talk.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I was able to find &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.benridgewoolworks.co.uk/&#34;&gt;a company&lt;/a&gt; that sells british fleeces and has a wash and dry service. Since I don&amp;rsquo;t have the energy to hand wash and rinse (at least twice) 1-3kg of wool and I definitely don&amp;rsquo;t have the space to dry it. (Glasgow has an &lt;a href=&#34;https://weather-and-climate.com/average-monthly-Humidity-perc,glasgow-gb,United-Kingdom&#34;&gt;average humidity of 79%&lt;/a&gt; over the year. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to dry laundry even with our dehumidifier on every day all year round.)&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;So, I ordered my first fleece! I decided on a beige &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shetland_sheep&#34;&gt;Shetland&lt;/a&gt;(the website said beige but I think it looks like &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shetland_sheep#Colours_and_patterns&#34;&gt;musket or moorit&lt;/a&gt; - either way, it&amp;rsquo;s not beige), which was maybe a bold choice for my first. Shetland sheep are a &amp;lsquo;primitive&amp;rsquo; breed, which basically means old/ not cross-bred in recent history. They have a double coat, with an outer hairy layer and a soft, downy undercoat. Both are usable, but I&amp;rsquo;ve decided to pull them apart and process them separately.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 1234; --h: 1640;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/fleece-closeup.png&#34; width=&#34;1234&#34; height=&#34;1640&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;A close-up of the fleece as it arrived, showing the crimpy, soft, undercoat on the left and some locks of the long, hairy outercoat on the right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where I&amp;rsquo;m at so far:&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;30g undercoat, carded and ready to spin&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;29g (undercoat) and 40g (outercoat), separated, not yet carded&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;li&gt;736g unseparated but mostly clean&lt;/li&gt;&#xA;&lt;/ul&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;figure class=&#34;&#34;&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &lt;div class=&#34;img-container&#34; style=&#34;--w: 1234; --h: 1648;&#34;&gt;&#xA;        &lt;img loading=&#34;lazy&#34; alt=&#34;A fleece in various stages of processing&#34; src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/lainland/posts/spinning/fleece-processing.png&#34; width=&#34;1234&#34; height=&#34;1648&#34;&gt;&#xA;    &lt;/div&gt;&#xA;&#xA;    &#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;em&gt;Bottom: around 1/3 of the total fleece, unseparated and as it arrived&#xA;Top right: separated wool, with the outercoat above and the undercoat below&#xA;Top left: carded undercoat ready to spin&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s a really beautiful fleece with a lot of colour variation and the undercoat is so so soft.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;I have plans for both the undercoat and the outercoat - more on that next time!&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;blockquote&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;Edit: In an earlier version of this post, I forgot to talk about the price of fleeces. Obviously they&amp;rsquo;re a lot cheaper than their weight in yarn. While the different yarns for my cardigan cost between £10 and £30 per 100g, the whole fleece plus the wash and dry service cost £25.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&#xA;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>